Okay, so pick up again, I'm sorry, from דף ל"ג. Daf Lamed
Gimmel. Today's דף Daf is ל"ג, Lamed Gimmel, we pick up beginning
of the fifth פרק, Perek, the bottom of ל"ב עמוד ב', Lamed
Bet Amud Bet, and just to remind you where we are, where
we have had the כהנים Kohanim doing now the תרומת הדשן, Terumat
Ha-deshen, cleaning, doing the דישון מזבח הפנימי Dishun Mizbe'ach Ha-penimi and the
דישון Dishun of the מנורה, Menorah, taking away the ashes, doing sort
of half, we'll find out about the other half in a bit,
and then finally the bringing of the תמיד, Tamid, the שחיטה, Shechting,
the sprinkling of the blood, where they did it in the various
rings that they used to hold the animal, the way they bound
the animal, and then the dismembering of it and the bringing up
of the various parts of the קרבן Korban to the halfway up
on the ramp. And then finally, now that they have done the
תמיד, Tamid, they go into the room, the לשכת הגזית, Lishkat Ha-gazit,
where they're going to do another lottery, but before they do that
other lottery, they first do a very quick דאוונען. Davening. And that's
what we did yesterday, we read the first משנה Mishnah where it
says that they did a קריאת שמע, Kriat Shema, they did three
ברכות, Brachot, אמת ויציב Emet Ve-yatziv which is גאל ישראל, Ga'al Yisrael,
two ברכות Brachot from the שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, one about the
עבודה, Avodah, one about the ברכת כהנים, Birkat Kohanim, not actually the
actual ברכת כהנים, Birkat Kohanim, and a special blessing that if it
was שבת Shabbat the leaving group gave to the entering group. Okay,
and now we move on. Yes. And we're talking about that.
We say that prayer is instead of כהנים, Kohanim, so I guess
it's not the עמידה Amidah that they're saying here, but still, this
is indicating that prayer pre-coexisted.
Right, and I appreciate you mentioning that, and I mentioned that at
the end of yesterday, but it was at the very end, that
I do think that this is, you know, very significant in terms
of thinking about the relationship between the two of them. For example,
just to mention another point about this that the מפרש Mefaresh here
says, the like Pseudo-רש"י Rashi said, he said that he emphasized in
the end of the last פרק Perek that when it says they
went to the לשכת הגזית Lishkat Ha-gazit to say the שמע, Shema,
he says specifically the reason is כדי שיתפללו קודם שיקטירו שום הקטר
יעלו כוונם לריח ניחוח. Kedei she-yitpallelu kodem she-yaktiru shum haktar ya'alu k'vannam
le-rei'ach nicho'ach.
It's appropriate they should pray, although you sprinkled the blood of the
תמיד, Tamid, it hasn't yet been put on the fire, the fire
having, the smoke hasn't gone up, you haven't done the קטורת, Ketoret,
all of this is a sense of it rising up to God
and you want that to be preceded by תפילה. Tefillah. So the
question is, you know, what does that mean that you want it
to be preceded by תפילה? Tefillah? Is it that the focus is
the קרבן, Korban, I would say this is the simple read, when
you're bringing קרבנות Korbanot the focus is the קרבן, Korban, but
what's the meaning of the קרבן? Korban? You want to frame it
in terms of your thoughts and your prayers, whatever, the way of
framing the same way, for example, you put your hands on the
חטאת Chatat and you do a וידוי Viduy on the חטאת, Chatat,
you do a confession. And the רמב"ם Rambam says that he thinks
that if you were bringing a שלמים, Shelamim, you would put your
hand on the שלמים Shelamim and you would say words of praise.
So you want your words to frame the significance and the two
ברכות Brachot that they made, other than גאל ישראל Ga'al Yisrael which
was about the שמע, Shema, but the two ברכות Brachot that they
made was one about the עבודה Avodah that the עבודת הקרבנות Avodat
Ha-korbanot should be accepted and the other was about the ברכת כהנים
Birkat Kohanim which is another role they're going to be playing. So
the two exact ברכות Brachot other than the one that's connected to
the שמע, Shema, the two ברכות Brachot that they made which are
these sort of distillation of שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei are very much
about the קרבנות Korbanot they're bringing, not something independent of that. But
nevertheless, even having said all that, even if that's true that the
תפילה Tefillah here is somehow framing, the fact that it's playing a
framing role means that it's of tremendous significance, that the קרבנות Korbanot
don't as it were speak for themselves, that the meaning of the
קרבנות Korbanot and the way in which they're sort of offered have
a lot to do with the words that you say and your
prayers and the way they're being framed. So I do think it
is a critical point that recognizing that even at this stage, you
know, almost one of the very first things that comes is the
תפילות Tefillot prior to the קרבנות. Korbanot.
And it was only the כהנים Kohanim that were praying.
Only the כהנים, Kohanim,
well, they were the ones that were offering the קרבנות. Korbanot. You
mean like let's say the ישראל Yisrael that were in the מעמד.
Ma'amad. Right, the people brought a
קרבן Korban they didn't pray.
Right,
we don't know about that. I mean, there's the מעמדות. Ma'amadot. Yes,
the מעמדות Ma'amadot speak about that in the גבולין, Gevulin, the מעמד
Ma'amad would have special readings of the תורה Torah and so on
according to the, right, meaning, you know, according to the משנה Mishnah
there definitely were, and another point that's implicitly being made here, you
know, Michael's pointing out and says אמת ויציב, Emet Ve-yatziv, which is
a classic obviously reflecting the classic נוסח Nusach of that ברכה Bracha
of שמע, Shema, an implicit point that's also being made is the
antiquity of תפילות, Tefillot, right? So it's not just the relationship of
תפילות Tefillot to קרבנות Korbanot but how far back the תפילות Tefillot
go. And Michael's correct in תענית Ta'anit where it talks about the
מעמדות, Ma'amadot, the sort of the representatives of ישראל Yisrael that went
to the מקדש, Mikdash, you know, you know, it was also broken
up into 24 groups and one went each week, and then there
were those representatives that were left behind, not everybody can travel to
ירושלים, Yerushalayim, and they had special readings of the תורה Torah and
so on, so there were, yes, the idea... idea of תפילות, Tfillot,
the antiquity of them and the way they corresponded to the שמונה
עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, you know, or to the עבודה Avodah is definitely
implicit here and I appreciate, you know, that you're sort of really
bringing that out. I will say for example that scholars think that,
you know, that the תהלים Tehillim served as a, you know, as
essentially an ancient prayer book. I mean that's certainly how it functions
today for like, you know, for a lot of people, you know,
and that, and that, and that a major role of תהלים Tehillim
was before you had a set form of תפילות Tfillot is that
you would pick the appropriate תהלים Tehillim to say and say it
as necessary. But yeah, look, prayer is a very profound human spiritual
need. I mean my god, it goes back to אברהם, Avraham, you
know, so the quest, or earlier to נח, Noach, you know, so
the question is when was it sort of made more statutory? When
was it made with a more fixed form? And that is, you
know, very much implicit in this משנה. Mishna. So yeah, very good
to bring that out. Okay, so let's take a look at now
the next משנה. Mishna. So we're in פרק ה משנה ב, Perek
He Mishna Bet, at the bottom of למד ב עמוד ב. Lamed
Bet Amud Bet. אמר להם. Amar Lahem.
So the person who was in charge of, you know, sort of
like I call him the floor manager, the ממונה, Memuneh, the appointed
one, the one who's in charge of distributing and overseeing all of
the jobs, he said to the כהנים Kohanim now that they're all
in the לשכת הגזית Lishkat HaGazit and they've done their quick דאווענען
Davening or their דאווענען Davening that relates to the קרבנות. Korbanot. חדשים
לקטורת, Chadashim L'Ketoret,
anybody who has not yet had a chance to bring the קטורת,
Ketoret, because this was seen as a סגולה Segula to make you
wealthy. So you would only get to do it once. So anybody
who has yet to have had a chance to bring the קטורת.
Ketoret. Of course it's a pretty interesting that idea that you only
had to do it once because you have to imagine how big,
if you're let's say been a כהן Kohen and been working for
the last fifty years, right, so how many times have you been
in the בית המקדש? Beit HaMikdash? Well really other than רגלים Regalim
you only there twice a year. So yeah, you only really needed
like a hundred כהנים Kohanim and you still wouldn't have had a
chance to do it more than once. Okay, anyway, anybody who's yet
to have had a chance to do the קטורת, Ketoret, בואו והפיסו,
Bo U'vifisu, come and be part of the lottery. זכה מי שזכה,
Zacha Mi Shezacha, so they did the lottery and the one who
won it, won it. אמר להם, Amar Lahem, so then he said,
the manager, whatever, the guy in
charge said, כהן Kohen in charge
said, חדשים אם ישנים, Chadashim Im Yeshanim, old ones and new ones,
בואו והפיסו, Bo U'vifisu,
let's go do a come for the next lottery. מי מעלה איברים
מן הכבש למזבח? Mi Maaleh Eivarim Min HaKeves LaMizbeach? We had put
all of the parts of the תמיד Tamid halfway up the ramp
or on the lower half. Who now, we're going to have another
lottery, who gets to bring them from the middle of the ramp
to the top?
This
is more כבוד? Kavod? Yeah, so that's why, exactly, and the מפרשים
Meforshim say that exactly, that the idea that there's so many involved
and there's yet another lottery, it makes a very big deal about
it and it also makes it sort of, brings attention to it.
Like if you did the whole thing straight up the ramp it
would be done before you, before you realized it. So you know,
it just gives it a lot more excitement.
But couldn't it induce more corruption with so many people?
Well it's not like it leads to personal enrichment. It's, you know,
just bringing it up to the ramp. Right, it's to show that
like, it's like when they auction off עליות Aliyot in שול, Shul,
you know,
it's a כבוד Kavod to do it, it's not a personal enrichment.
Yeah, bit more normal. Right, exactly.
I would have thought that whoever started it would finish it?
Well, good, you could be, you could be רבי אליעזר בן יעקב.
Rabbi Eliezer Ben Yaakov. רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer Ben Yaakov
אומר המעלה איברים לכבש הוא מעלה אותם על גבי המזבח. Omer HaMaaleh
Eivarim LaKeves Hu Maaleh Otam Al Gabei HaMizbeach. Whoever brought it halfway
up gets to bring it from the half to the top. But
he still said there were two stages even though there wasn't another
lottery.
התחיל במצוה אומרים לו גמור. Hitchil B'Mitzva Omrim Lo Gemor.
There you go now משנה ג. Mishna Gimel. מסרו לחזנים. Masru L'Chazzanim.
Now this משנה, Mishna, I got to tell you, I find very
fascinating or a little curious actually. Now they're done. So now you
know okay, so now we've got who are the כהנים Kohanim doing
the next stage, you got ten more כהנים Kohanim bringing the stuff
up and we got some כהנים Kohanim who are going to do
the קטורת Ketoret and now what happened to the other כהנים Kohanim
at this stage? Well I would think what happened to the other
כהנים, Kohanim, they're waiting around until they open up the עזרה Azarah
until ישראל Yisrael comes in for all the קרבנות. Korbanot. Wait, did
they not done the other five, the other תנובות? Tnuvot? Because we're
getting there,
we're getting there. Okay. מסרו לחזנים, Masru L'Chazzanim, so they handed them,
presumably the remainder of the כהנים, Kohanim, over to the חזנים Chazzanim
which were obviously like the assistants or again I don't know if
here חזנים Chazzanim means people that are more sort of assistants or
more people in charge of the מנורה? Menorah? Yeah, no, or like
assisting them, assisting the other כהנים. Kohanim. Not exactly clear to me
how much the חזנים Chazzanim whether they, whether it was a status
of authority or more of sort of of like an assistant.
But they're כהנים Kohanim though, these חזנים? Chazzanim?
Presumably, I mean they're in the מקדש Mikdash and so on. So
yes, definitely presumably. Okay,
so they gave them over to the חזנים, Chazzanim, היו מפשיטים אותם
את בגדיהם, Hayu Mafshitim Otam Et Bigdeihem, and the חזנים Chazzanim would
sort of undress, I don't know why they couldn't undress themselves, but
again it's a sign of כבוד Kavod which makes me, which hits
the point I was saying before about whether the חזנים Chazzanim is
a position of authority or the opposite. Anyway, they would take the
כהנים's, Kohanim they would have the כהנים Kohanim get undressed from their
בגדי כהונה, Bigdei Kehuna, ולא היו מניחים עליהם אלא מכנסיים בלבד, V'Lo
Hayu Manichim Aleihem Ela Michnasayim Bilvad, and they would only leave on
them their underpants alone. underwear. Well, that's a good thing. But according
to the גמרא, Gemara, actually then what they would do is they
would put on their their non-בגדי כהונה, Bigdei Kehunah, which would be
like a toga, a cloak or whatever, and then they would take
off their underwear from underneath, and there which is their בגדי כהונה,
Bigdei Kehunah, their מכנסיים Michnasayim breeches if you want. And then they'd
put on their their בגדי חול Bigdei Chol underwear. So obviously they
wouldn't be naked.
These are the ones who are done?
These are the ones who are not doing anything right now. Okay?
והחלונות היו שם, V'hachalonot hayu sham, and there were little cubbies, is
really what החלונות hachalonot means, little cubbies. וכתוב עליהם תשמיש הכלים, V'chatuv
aleihem tashmish hakeilim, and there it said the use of the כלים,
keilim, which is basically explained to me: one cubby said hats, and
the other cubby said breeches, and the other one said, you know,
said cloaks. But again, like, what? They can't wait like an hour
until, you know, everything is done and then they open up the
gates and everybody comes? But you know, who knows, maybe it was
early in the morning, says: "Okay guys, you don't have to do
anything, go get a cup of coffee, see you back in an
hour." I really don't get why they are undressing at this stage
just because they're not doing anything right now. They're going to come
back and do something? I don't know, I made that up. Well,
yeah, they're not done for the day. I mean, did they have
to wear the בגדי חול Bigdei Chol for half an hour?
Well, right. I mean, the only reason I would say they'd have
to wear their בגדי חול Bigdei Chol is if, you know, we
had the discussion before whether בגדי כהונה ניתנו ליהנות בהם, Bigdei Kehunah
nitnu l'henot bahem, if they were allowed to lounge around... right? I
was sort of being a little bit facetious, go to Starbucks get
a coffee, but if they wanted to lounge around, or maybe they
did want to take a little walk around הר הבית Har Habayit
or something, so they can't be doing it in בגדי כהונה. Bigdei
Kehunah. But it's still funny, 'cause you would think that they would
just be standing, waiting. But you know, who knows, they gave 'em
a break at that time.
All right, people who were done with their... whatever it is, what
did they do? They didn't have to take off their בגדי כהונה?
Bigdei Kehunah?
People done with what?
Like whoever was, you know, the guy who was מעלה איברים לכבש.
ma'aleh evarim lakevesh.
To the כבש? kevesh?
Yeah, so he's
not working at the next stage, then he also gets to switch
clothes, yeah. Gets dressed down in his street clothes, in his street
clothes if you would. Right, so everybody who's not working now. Okay,
so wait, the cubbies,
did they belong to individuals?
Right, and they would...
that's an interesting point because we do say, that's a very good
point because we do say מידו בד שהיא כמידתו, mido bad shehi
k'midato, that it's supposed to have... it has to be to size.
So maybe they had cubbies of different sizes. What size are you?
Size nine, a size ten, what are you?
I know, but they did have to be according to their height.
The גמרא's Gemara clear about that, שהיא כמידתו. shehi k'midato. So even
if they're sort of like
one size fits all, because,
yeah, I don't know, the hats... I don't know, you think the
same point of שהיא כמידתו shehi k'midato applies to the hats? They
say it about the tunic, that it had to be according to
the length. But you know, maybe you're right, maybe it's like when
you go to the bowling alley, right?
You just tell them the size and they give you one. But
they still had their own underwear. That is true, but, you know,
I guess they laundered it. Okay, מי שזכה בקטורת. Mi shezachah b'ketoret.
Now we... so now we get to bringing the קטורת. ketoret. Okay,
so we brought the תמיד, Tamid, we didn't burn these parts, but
we actually sprinkled the blood. And next is קטורת. ketoret. מי שזכה
בקטורת היה נוטל את הכף. Mi shezachah b'ketoret hayah notel et hakaf.
So he would take the כף, kaf, which is like, you know,
a... whatever, a... not a pan, what would you call it? A
ladle? A ladle, I guess, yeah. No, more of a ladle, more
of a ladle. Okay. והכף דומה לתרקב גדול. V'hakaf domeh l'tarkav gadol.
It was like a big תרקב. tarkav. So if you know what
a תרקב tarkav is, which is a certain type of a thing
used for carrying, like we said it's a two-קב kav carrying container.
So that's what this is. I don't know, I imagine it... the
reason I said a pan is I imagine it like a sort
of like a... like, you know, like what you have on your...
your... your stovetop, right? So it's obviously got some depth to it,
but it's got a handle to hold onto it. So that's the
way I imagine it. Anyway, של זהב. shel zahav. Now that was
gold. ומחזקת שלשת קבין. U'machazeket shloshet kabin. It's going to hold three
קבין kavin of קטורת ketoret in it. And the... הבזך היה...... v'habazach
hayah... now the actual קטורת ketoret wasn't directly in this larger pan.
What was it in? הבזך היה בתוכו. habazach hayah betocho. הבזך, Habazach,
which was a smaller pan. So again, the way I just imagine
this is like, you know, when you stack your... you know, your
pans... in your kitchen, you know, so a small one fits in
the bigger one. They all have handles to help you manipulate them.
So the small one was מלא וגדוש קטורת. malei v'gadush ketoret. It
was filled and overflowing. It was like, you know, it had a
mound of קטורת. ketoret. וכיסוי היה לו. V'chisuy hayah lo. Now why
did you have a small pan in a big pan? Because if
your small pan has a mound of קטורת, ketoret, you're afraid it's
going to spill. It's hard to be steady with that as you're
walking. So it gets caught in the bigger pan. Why not just
put it all in the bigger pan? Because it's more כבודיק kovodik
to show you're bringing like this full, you know, mound of קטורת
ketoret filling up a whole pan rather than just having some stuff
lying at the bottom of a bigger pan. So but you have
it in the bigger so if it overflows it gets caught. וכיסוי
היה לו מלמעלה. V'chisuy hayah lo milma'alah. וכיסוי היה לו. V'chisuy hayah
lo. It had a cover. Which had a cover?
It's not exactly clear. How do you have a cover if it's
overflowing? I mean, okay, maybe it had a flat cover, maybe it's
more of like a, you know, some type of a dome cover.
וכמין מטולטלת היה עליו. U'k'min mitulteles hayah alav. וכמין מטולטלת היה עליו
מלמעלה, U-k'min metulteles hayah alav mil-malah, and there was a מטולטלת. metulteles.
What's a מטולטלת? metulteles? Some say it means like a ring. Again,
using the oven pot—pot is what I want to say, not pan.
That's why I was getting confused because pan is flatter. Okay, so
it's more like a pot. Okay, so you have a bigger pot
and a smaller pot. Of course, they're made out of gold or
whatever, so they're very beautiful. But anyway, a bigger one and a
smaller one. Now, if you know on top of your pot you
have a cover, what do you have on top of the cover
of your pot? A handle. So that's the מטולטלת. metulteles. So some
say it's actually like a metal handle, some say it's like a
cloth handle, some say... a potholder? What? Pot holder? Right, could be
the pot holder. Although you didn't have hot stuff in this, you
had קטורת ketores stuff. The hot stuff will be in the next
one.
Wasn't everything gold like the rest of it?
Well, some say it was. It was out of metal, maybe it
was out of gold. Okay, but some specifically say it was like
cloth. Some say the רמב"ם Rambam says it means no, there was
one cover for the smaller pot where the קטורת ketores was in,
and then there was a cloth covering on top of the larger
pot. So he learns these as two separate things, not as a
handle.
So no one actually saw the קטורת ketores because it was all
covered.
Well, oh, that's a good point, because regardless, even without the רמב"ם,
Rambam, you mean that there was a cover over it. That's a
good point. Unless they made it out of glass, but you would
think they would have said that. Yeah, that's a very good point.
These details really seem to be eyewitness accounts.
Yeah, how would they know this? Right, right. All those little details.
That's a very good point. Yeah. Alright, so now משנה ה. Mishnah
hey. So now we've got the קטורת ketores being tucked in like
a gold pot inside of a larger pot.
Sorry, how much was a קב kav again? A קב kav was...
yeah, I don't know, I should have looked it up.
Yeah, I don't know, a קב. kav. רביעית, revi'is, הין hin and
הין, hin,
I don't know. I can't tell you off the top of my
head. Okay, anyway. Okay, so, and you know these golden pots in
which the קטורת ketores was in, the smaller one inside of the
larger one. משנה ה: מי שזכה במחתה נטל מחתת הכסף. Mishnah hey:
Mi she-zachah be-machtah natal machtas ha-kesef. Now
one person got not only the קטורת, ketores, but the shoveling of
the coals. Now it's interesting, he didn't say who won that. Some
say that it was the choice of the one who won the
קטורת ketores to pick somebody who would get to come with him
to do the coals. And some say maybe the guy next to
him got the option to do the coals because you need one
person to actually, you know, put the קטורת ketores on the coals,
but you need the other person to bring the coals into the
inner מזבח. mizbeach. So the person who got the merit with the
מחתה, machtah, which is like the shovel, נטל מחתת הכסף, natal machtas
ha-kesef,
he took a silver shovel, ועלה לראש המזבח, ve-alah le-rosh ha-mizbeach,
he went to the top of the altar, ופינה את הגחלים הילך
והילך, u-finah es ha-gechalim hilech ve-hilech, and he moved the, you know,
coals aside to get to some good, you know,
coals in the middle.
So he moved this, this big...
he went back on the outer מזבח. mizbeach. Right, the inner מזבח
mizbeach had no regular burning fire. It got its coals from coals
on the outer מזבח. mizbeach. Okay. And if you remember, like if
you see this picture here, there was a special fire just for
producing the coals to be used for the קטורת. ketores. And that
fire was closer to the side, was in the west, closer to
the היכל. Heichal. And it was closer because,
not just to make it convenient, but just to symbolize its that
it's being used there for the קטורת. ketores. So he went to
the top, he got some nice coals, חתה, chasah,
he shoveled them, ירד ועירם לתוך של זהב. yarad ve-iram le-soch shel
zahav. And then he poured these coals from his silver shovel into
a gold shovel. The reason he says that he used silver and
then gold is because you don't want gold is very precious, you
don't want it, the shoveling or whatever, would wear it away. Of
course, if Charlie was here, he would tell us that the silver
would probably corrode more than the gold, but I don't know. Anyway,
okay, so now you've got it, you shoveled it in a silver
shovel, now you've got it in a gold shovel. So you have
one person with... withstanding the heat? Yeah, that's what Charlie's been saying.
Oh, it could or could not, or maybe it's the difference between
corroding and withstanding the heat. Yeah, anyway, I mean, by the way,
can you make anything out of pure gold? It's too malleable, right?
So even when they say gold here, it's got to be some
gold alloy. But anyway.
Yeah,
that's true too.
Or you can make it very thin. Aha.
Yeah,
but if he's like touching hot coals on a metal thing, wouldn't
he...
how's he... yeah, that's
a good point. Maybe it had a cloth handle, but the problem
is is that you can't have a חציצה chatzitzah between the כהן
kohen and the כלי שרת, kli shares,
unless of course... but it's questions if it's done לכבוד. lik-vod. There's
a whole discussion of let's say that something is done there לכבוד,
lik-vod, but this isn't exactly לכבוד, lik-vod, it's just for pragmatic practical
reasons. That's a good question. I mean, I assume if your handle
is far enough apart, separate, no? If you have a very long
handle, you don't think that would work? And you're not leaving it
like in the oven, you know, it's a few minutes, you shoveled
it, it's a few minutes. I imagine you could do it. Alright.
24 ביצים. beitzim. 24 ביצים. beitzim. Okay. 24 ביצים. beitzim.
No,
6 לוג. log.
And a לוג log
is a... so
okay, so that's right. So a רביעית, revi'is, four... there are
four רביעיות revi'iyos in a לוג. log. What?
Four? Four. So how much? A קב? kav? Is six ביצים beitzim
in a לוג, log,
four לוג log in a קב, kav, six קב kav in a
סאה. se'ah.
Okay, 24 eggs. That is three קב. kavs. How big
are those eggs?
He's
carrying a lot of eggs. Wow. Yeah.
Well, the thing carries three קב, kav, it wasn't full. It had
in it, it had in it the בזך bazach which has so
that so
it says, yeah.
Now wait, right. No, he said 24 eggs is a קב, kav,
right? Is one קב, kav, he's carrying three קב. kavs. Three קב.
kavs.
No, but
it's a three קב kav container.
No, the three קב kav container didn't say how big the בזך
bazach was. It was a three קב kav container of 72 eggs,
which is pretty big, that's true. I mean, I don't know, is
that is that bigger than like the biggest pot you have in
your kitchen, like your soup pot?
Just remember an egg is if you have a bunch of eggs
you have a lot of air. Right.
Right. I think it's about the size of your soup pot, okay?
But he has the בזך bazach in it.
And that one and right, and then the בזך bazach of the
קטורת ketores was in that.
We don't know how much was in there.
Right. Okay, I mean, what was in it was the amount that
sort of, well actually the
בזך bazach was מלא malei because he
said, well we don't know how much was the בזך. bazach. No,
there was a there was a מנה. maneh. Hold on. I'll tell
you how much was in it. Right. Right. Right. How much is
a מנה? maneh?
So a מנה maneh was half of a
מנה, maneh, whatever that was. Okay. I don't know. It was half
in the morning half in the afternoon. So we will find out
how much of a מנה maneh was.
Now, somebody else brings it to the מזבח.
mizbe'ach. He is.
Everybody's putting it on the המחתה ha-machtah guy does it?
Or is that not? No, you will find out. They both are
involved in it. The מחתה machtah guy puts the coals on the
מזבח mizbe'ach and the קטורת ketores person puts the קטורת ketores on
the coals. Okay. So now, נתפזר nitpazer ממנו mimmennu כקב kekav גחלים.
gechalim. Now, how much
how much of coals did they have? If you remember before, it
says that the fire was big enough for five קב kavs of
coals, five excuse me, קב kav of coals. He shoveled out four
קב kav and then he poured it into a gold one that
would contain three קב. kav. So that's why a קב kav would
scatter because the gold was a קב kav smaller than the than
the silver. So there would a קב kav would scatter. Now how
did they? On the מזבח? mizbe'ach? No, no, no, they are he
comes down from the outer altar with his silver silver shovel filled
with four קב kav of coals. He pours it into a gold
shovel that contains that has the three קב kav capacity. And therefore
one קב kav of coals spills off and on the ground and
we'll talk in a minute what he does with it. And now
he's going to bring the three קב kav of coals into the
into the היכל, heichal, okay, in his gold shovel. Now how big
is a קב? kav? Do you know how big a קב kav
is? Oh we had the קב kav before, it was the same
קב. kav. Okay, so the same size of the shovel is the
size of that's interesting, it just okay, so the same size of
the shovel
is the size of the pot, the larger pot in which is
the smaller one of the קטורת. ketores. So basically you've got a
shovel with a capacity of let's say like your soup pot, that's
three קב, kavs, that's one כהן kohen with that's gold one with
the coals. And you have
another כהן kohen with a gold pot the size of a soup
pot and in it is a smaller pot that has your קטורת.
ketores. Okay? So that's I think a pretty clear picture there. So
they're both carrying something the size of a gold pot of your
soup pot.
Why didn't he do
it on top of the מזבח? mizbe'ach? Why didn't he do it
on top of the מזבח?
mizbe'ach? To take the coals, put it in your thing, with whatever
scattered.
I don't know, to manipulate two of the two of the כלי
שרת klei shares at the top and I'm not sure. It's interesting.
I don't know. Okay.
I I also
think it was like the idea of like half, you know, doing
half top and then half the rest, it like makes things very
busy and a lot of sort of things. If everything's going on
top of מזבח mizbe'ach you don't see what it what's going on.
Okay. So so one קב kav of גחלים gechalim spilled out. 24
eggs. והיה ve-hayah מכבדן mechabedan לאמה. la-amah. He would sweep them away,
they they must have had brooms, they would sweep them away into
the אמה. amah. The אמה amah was basically, like I said, this
is where you know in Israel, you know how they do, you
know how they how they mop the floors, right? They squeegee it
into a hole in the floor. So this they they got it
from the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. There was apparently, there was apparently
some type of a trench in which there was water flowing, and
that's where they sort of you know, pushed all the blood into.
And they also pushed these גחלים gechalim into. And then it flowed
away and it flowed into some type of a river outside of
the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Yeah, I don't know, I was wondering
if they were going to show it in the picture. I don't
see them showing it anywhere. Anyways, that's what they did. So they
swept it into the אמה. amah. ובשבת u-ve-Shabbos היה hayah כופה kofeh
עליהן alehen פסכתר. psach-tar. And when שבת Shabbos
they would put on top of it a some type of a
pot again. The פסכתר psach-tar is another type of a pot, a
larger one, okay, because on שבת Shabbos you can't do it, it's
מוקצה, muktzah, also maybe it would accidentally cause them to go out,
but certainly it's מוקצה muktzah and against the classic understanding that there
are no דרבנןs d'rabanan in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, that's only
when it gets away in the עבודה. avodah. Now you might think
this gets away in the עבודה, avodah, you've got this pot has
to step over the whole time, right? But apparently
not, apparently that was a it
was they were able to manage. So they put a pot on
top of it. Maybe on account of סכנה sakanah either. Right. Yeah.
Yeah. Okay anyway ופסכתר היתה כלי גדול *u'pasachter haysa kli gadol*
fine
here it describes you what it was. It was a big vessel,
so it's bigger than, it's a stock pot, not just your soup
pot, it's like whatever, much, it's very large מחזקת לתך *machazekes letech*.
So it would contain a לתך *letech*. גדול *gadol* how much is
a לתך *letech*? It's more than, it's more than three קב *kav*,
I'll tell you that.
Do you find how much the מנה *maneh* was?
I didn't see the מנה *maneh*. There's a Greek, it's half a
כור *kor* or something? Okay
it's half a כור *kor* which is fifteen סאה *se'ah* and ninety
קב *kav*.
Ninety קב *kav*.
Okay, so wow. So that is considerably larger. It's thirty times the
size. We were saying the three קב *kav* was a soup pot,
this is thirty times the size. This is like, this is not
a pot, this is like a huge type of a metal vat,
right? Okay. So that was, that's good for proportion. Okay. So it
was, that's how big it was. It was thirty times the size
of our soup pot. ושתי שרשרות היו בה *u'shtei sharsheros hayu bah*.
And there it had two chains. אחת שהוא מושך בה ויורד *achas
shehu moshech bah v'yored* one to draw it down ואחת שהוא אוחז
מלמעלה *v'achas shehu ocheiz milma'alah* and the other to hold it up.
What does that mean? בשביל שלא תתגלגל *bishvil shelo sisgalgel* so it
shouldn't roll. So basically this is how they removed the ashes from,
not the coals which was a small thing as we said. When
they had to undig the ashes down off the מזבח Mizbeach *mizbei'ach*
how would they do it? So they had a huge, you know
thing, and they put it on, into this huge, I don't even,
I can't even call it a pot, whatever it is, a vat
almost, cauldron, right? Oh, that's a good one, right? So like, you
know like the witches brew type thing, anyway, that's probably what it
is because it sounds like that. Anyway, they filled that up with
ashes and then they had to take it down. Now it's not
a one-person job and you certainly can't carry it. So one person
pulled and the other person held on the top with the other
rope to, or the other chain to keep it stable, and they,
they pulled it down the, the ramp like that. Okay. I don't
know why they didn't have wheels on it, but maybe that כלי
*kli* can't, you know, that wouldn't have fit.
Attached to the ramp or?
No, it wasn't. No, I for a while with the chains I
was thinking it was like a pulley system but no, then they
couldn't put it on top of the coals. No, no, it was
a large cauldron which just had a chain on each handle, if
you imagine, filled it up with ashes, now you have to take
this large cauldron down a ramp. How are you going to do
it? So one guy's going to hold the chain at the top,
the other guy's going to be pulling the chain at the bottom
and they're, at the other chain, and they're going to be slowly
walking down, they'll pull it down. Right, they didn't have wheels. They're
going to pull it down. Now you wonder like why didn't they
put it on a, you know, what do we call those things,
those little flat things with wheels? Dolly. It's true. That trolley,
whatever. I don't know. Would have made things easier.
But they've already done all this moving the ashes? You what?
No, no, this is just telling you now that we mentioned this
כלי *kli* we're telling you what they used it for. When they
would remove the ashes. That wouldn't be a daily thing. When they
would remove the ashes they'd use this big כלי *kli*.
And then, so I guess they wouldn't necessarily be doing it on
שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* because if you're using it to cover up these
coals then you couldn't use it on...
Right. Anyway, ובשלשה דברים היתה משמשת *u'bishlosha devarim haysa meshamashes*. This big
cauldron would be used for three things. כופין אותה על גבי גחלים
*kofin osah al gabei gechalim*. You would put it on top of
the, you know, the coals on שבת Shabbat, *Shabbos* which as I
said, מוקצה *muktzah*, כיבוי *kibuy* whatever, ועל השרץ בשבת *v'al ha'sheretz b'Shabbos*.
Also if you found a dead rodent in the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash: *Beis Hamikdash* on שבת *Shabbos*. It's טמא tamei *tamei*.
Now what do they and...
Right, now again, yeah, it's מוקצה *muktzah*. So again, it's interesting, you
would think it's more important to remove rodents, I mean, even though
it's not like it's מטמא *metamei* the מקדש *Mikdash*, but symbolically it's
very disturbing, and somebody accidentally might touch it. They were okay with
just putting a pot on top of it and waiting until after
שבת *Shabbos*. Again, why you needed such a large thing, I guess
because you didn't want somebody tripping over it. Either tripping over it
and uncovering it, or tripping over it and tripping. So if you
have a huge thing, nobody's going to trip over a huge cauldron.
Okay. One minute. ומורידים בה את הדשן מעל גבי המזבח *u'moridim bah
es hadeshen mei'al gabei hamizbei'ach*. And what we described before, they would
take it, use it to get the ashes off of the altar
when they did that. Maybe they did it only once a week,
but whenever they took the ashes off from the big ash pile,
not the תרומת הדשן terumat hadeshen *trumas hadeshen*. The one that they
did, you know, the תרומת הדשן terumat hadeshen, *trumas hadeshen* was symbolic.
The big ash pile which was done more infrequently.
And that's trapping the animal?
Dead.
All right,
right. If it weren't dead, or a cushion? Yeah, that would be
מוקצה *muktzah*. But you wonder like what about, what about טלטול מן
הצד *tiltul min hatzad*, like, you know, מוקצה *muktzah* if you do
it like with the back of your hand, with your foot, you
know, why isn't it like a גרף של רעי *graf shel re'i*,
like if you have like a pile of, of, you know,
excrement, you're allowed to remove it. So it's funny you would have
thought that there are other ways they could have actually removed it.
So does that mean like let's say if you find a cockroach
in your apartment or something like that, you can't like get rid
of it?
But this is... Yeah, I know. It's funny. I don't know. Are
we allowed, we're allowed to do that? Yeah,
with your back of your hand and using גרף של רעי *graf
shel re'i*. That's right. It's true. I mean nowadays you would have
definitely found, you know, I don't know the answer to that. You
know, maybe sometimes they wanted to be more מחמיר *machmir* on שבת
*Shabbos* than they had to be, because to counterbalance the fact that
Exactly. Okay. הגיעו בין האולם ולמזבח. Higiu bein ha'ulam v'lamizbeach. No, it
doesn't say it was of gold. הגיעו—that Higiu would
be
a
lot of
gold,
but maybe—הגיעו בין האולם ולמזבח.
Higiu bein ha'ulam v'lamizbeach. They came to the space between the אולם.
Ulam. The אולם Ulam is the, you know, is the not the
ante-chamber,
what's the room for that? We call it a hall. What? Vestibule
is probably a good word, right? Before you get to the היכל
Heichal itself. Okay, and this is the space בין האולם ולמזבח. bein
ha'ulam v'lamizbeach. Betwixt—it's like, you know, this is
like—there's something symbolic about that, we're going to talk in a minute
about how when they did certain עבודות, avodot, the כהנים Kohanim had
to remove themselves from that space. It's like you're like, you know,
it's the anticipatory space. You're still in the עזרה, Azara, but like
you're right between the מזבח Mizbeach. and the אולם, Ulam, you're right
before entering into the place of the היכל. Heichal. Okay, that's also
where you had the כיור, Kiyor, where you had the laver. Okay,
so they got to, so this is now the כהן Kohen with
the coals and the כהן Kohen with the קטורת. Ketoret. הגיעו בין
האולם ולמזבח. bein ha'ulam v'lamizbe'ach
So they came to the space between the אולם Ulam and the
מזבח. mizbe'ach, נטל אחד את המגריפה וזרקה בין האולם ולמזבח. natal echad
et hamagreifa v'zarka bein ha'ulam v'lamizbeach.
Some person took the מגריפה. magreifa. What is מגריפה? magreifa? מגריפה magreifa
could just mean a shovel.
It could mean—we learned before in a משנה Mishnah that it was
also the word for one of the כלי שרת Klei Shareit was
called a מגריפה. magreifa. Maybe it looked like a shovel, I don't
know exactly what it was. And some say it was that there
was a third thing about a מגריפה, magreifa, which is being referred
to here, which was some very large thing that would cause a
lot of—a lot of noise. Because here's what—here's what they did with
it. He took the מגריפה, magreifa, the shovel, literally, וזרקה בין האולם
ולמזבח. v'zarka bein ha'ulam v'lamizbeach. Threw it into that space. Why? Why?
It was basically like hitting a gong, okay, as we're about to
see. So I imagine that it's more like a big gong, maybe
you throw it into that space. That makes a lot of noise.
אין אדם שומע קול חברו בירושלים מקול המגריפה. Ein adam shomeia kol
chaveiro b'Yerushalayim mikol hamagreifa.
So we heard about other things that went all the way to
יריחו—when Yericho this מגריפה magreifa hit, you know, you couldn't hear your
friend speaking to you because of the sound of this. ולשלושה דברים
הייתה משמשת. U'lishlosha devarim hayta m'shameshet.
And it served three things.
Is it sort of an early alarm clock, because it's early in
the morning?
Well, exactly. It did—it did three things. כהן ששומע את קולה, Kohen
sheshomeia et kolah, because now you knew what was happening. This happened
like—okay, they already did the תמיד, Tamid, okay,
and you know—and you heard, remember, the opening of the doors of
the עזרה, Azara, which was heard all the way to יריחו, Yericho,
so you know the תמיד Tamid is starting. But now you're hearing
this—it's getting even closer to the time where you're really about to
be open for business. Like, this was all the stuff they did
before they opened the main doors and let the people in. Right?
They opened the עזרה, Azara, they didn't—I mean, the, you
know—so it doesn't sound like they've yet the people in. They're not
open, and they're not open—I mean, excuse me, I mean they did
open the doors to the עזרה, Azara, but it still doesn't sound
like people are there yet.
A contrast to the High Priest that has these little bells on
his— Oh,
that's interesting. That's right, more elegant.
That's true, but it still is the idea of having the voice
sounded. You know, I'm going to get back to that because that
ties into something I was about to say. But so they're doing
all of this stuff, right, that before it sounds like anybody from
the outside is let in. So first, the first warning was the
opening of the gates of the עזרה. Azara. Now you hear this
because after you're done with the קטורת— Ketoret No, the gates
of the עזרה Azara or was it the gates of the היכל
Heichal that made that big noise?
I'm sorry, you're right, you're right.
That's what I was saying before, I got confused, I'm sorry.
You're right. The—they—right, so the first noise, that's right. Okay, fine. Rewind.
Thank you.
So before when they got started, right, they opened that—those doors of
the היכל Heichal and then they got started with all their stuff
about the, you know, about the תרומת הדשן and so on. But
they have yet, thank you, to open up the doors of the
עזרה. Azara. Okay, so they're not yet open for business. Right, let's
take a step back. What have they done? They've opened the doors
of the—of the—of the היכל, Heichal, all the—you know,
so that was heard all the way to יריחו. Yericho. That's when
sort of the business started for the כהנים. Kohanim. They did the
תרומת הדשן, they did the—the שחיטה shechita of the תמיד—that Tamid took
time to dismember it and so on. Right, bringing it from halfway—the
other half, from halfway up the ramp to the top is going
to be relatively quickly. The time was in the whole, you know,
slicing it open and dismembering. And now they're moving to the stage
where, you know, they're—they're getting very close to really opening for business.
So that's what I—the way I understand, that's why this second alarm
thing, you know, is happening is that now everybody is hearing this
and pretty soon they're going to open—right, they've opened the doors of
the היכל, Heichal, but they haven't opened yet the doors of the
עזרה. Azara. So pretty soon they're going to open the doors of
the עזרה Azara and this is waking everybody up, like okay we're
about to really start, you know, being open for the public. So
you've been in like a department store, you know, you go—you know,
like this—it's probably half an hour, an hour before they open for
the public that they're getting everybody ready, everything—everybody's doing their jobs, there's
a lot of jobs to do, but now they're about to be
open for the
public.
Okay. In a religious context, you have, you know,
church towers often have bells that mark
time. Uh-huh. I remember when the cathedral—there were two of
them— Uh-huh, right. Each evening they used to— So this is kind
of a crossover between marking the time and a... it's marking time
with a religious bent.
Right, but I would say maybe it's also what I thought you
were going to say, it's also a little bit like of the
inverse because the church marks the time because based on certain times
is when the priests have to do certain like, you know, prayers
as you said and certain מצוות mitzvos and such. Here, as opposed
to the time dictating when things are done, I mean to some
degree you get started when it's the morning star, whatever, you know,
when it's the עלות, Alos, but, but when you are up to
a certain point, that designates the time. The time is designated, you
know, by when you're at the certain stage of the עבודה. avodah.
So there's a certain interesting inverse of that.
Well, you know, but I think that's just the modern invention of
the clock and timepieces because now, you know, שבת is at 6:57.
Right, I
understand, I understand. But it certainly is being marked when they got
up to something. Okay, so right,
Jewish time. Exactly what time? It starts when I get there. Right.
Okay, anyway, it's a good point. Okay,
that's one of the benefits of being a lecturer. It never starts
before you get there. Okay, anyway, so it says like this. Okay,
so ושלשה דברים היתה משמשת. v'shlosha devarim hayesa meshamashes. And this gong
or whatever it was would serve three things. כהן ששומע קולה יודע
שאחיו הכהנים נכנסים להשתחוות. Kohen sheshomea kohl-ah yodea she'echiv hakohenim nichnasim lishishtachavos.
When you hear this, you know that it's going to be about
time to go in and to do and to prostrate yourself. We'll
find out about this in the later משניות, mishnayos, but like things
are about to get busy. So if you're another כהן, kohen, you
find out, oh my God, it's about time to do like this
whole prostration, the השתחויה, hishtachavaya,
that's coming up, והוא רץ ובא, v'hu ratzu ba, you get run
and get and get ready. Now I've got a big question here.
We just
learned they took off their בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna and now we're
learning that a few minutes later after scooping some coals, you've got
to run and start getting ready. So what ever happened to the
coffee break before? I still don't get why they took off their
בגדי כהונה, bigdei kehuna, I have to tell you. ובן לוי ששומע
קולה יודע שאחיו הלווים נכנסים לדבר בשיר. Uben Levi sheshomea kohl-ah yodea
she'echiv haleviim nichnasim ledaber bashir. Did I say phrase לדבר
בשיר? ledaber bashir? Anyway, when the לוי Levi hears this, he's like,
oh my gosh, we're almost up. So they get run and getting
ready. What?
Who were they? הלווים. Leviim.
Yeah, we'll talk about that later. They get ready and they get
running to start to, you know, prepare for them to stand on
the דוכן duchan and to do their music and their singing. והוא
רץ ובא, v'hu ratzu ba, he runs and gets ready. וראש המעמד
היה מעמיד את הטמאים בשער מזרח. Verosh hamaamad haya maamid es hatmeim
beshaar mizrach. Now this is fascinating. The head of the מעמד, maamad,
the מעמד maamad presumably means the ישראלים Yisraelim who were there as
representatives of the people. He would stand the טמאי tamei people in
front of... in the eastern gate. That's the gate that has not
been opened or the eastern gate, the gate of the עזרה. azara.
Now what does that mean? Why would he do that? So most
commentators, be ready to be upset, Rivka, most commentators say, not about
women, but just in general, maybe not. Most commentators say it means
he would take out the כהנים Kohanim that had become טמא tamei
and maybe the own ישראלים Yisraelim who had been טמא tamei, and
he would put them up there. Why? In order to... a debate.
One is in order to embarrass them. Look at this, you were
so negligent, you allowed yourself to become טמא, tamei, today was your
day to work and that's like a public shaming. This is debated
in the גמרא. Gemara. And others say it was the opposite. It
was... Gemara says, quoted Gemara, you might think... the other
and some say it was the opposite, which is that people will
say, hey, where's John? He's not here. He was supposed to work
today. Why isn't he? So you put him up there so everybody
sees, look everybody, these people are טמאים, tameim, they have a reason
that they're off, that they're not going to be working today. So
the opposite, it was so people wouldn't be upset and curious why
they weren't working today. So the רמב"ם Rambam says that's one explanation,
which seems to be the consensus. The רמב"ם Rambam says it's very
different. כהנים Kohanim and maybe the ישראלים Yisraelim who were part of
the מעמד, maamad, oh because it says ראש המעמד. Rosh Hamaamad. Although
sometimes the ראש המעמד Rosh Hamaamad means just the person assigned to
this and it doesn't mean the ישראל מעמד Yisrael Maamad because again,
the ישראלים Yisraelim are presumably not there yet. So what are they
doing? What's the ראש המעמד Rosh Hamaamad doing
together? Busy
whatever. Yeah. So רמב"ם Rambam says what it means is, it was
outside of the שער העזרה. Shaar haAzara. He heard this voice, he
knew what was starting, right? Because you hear the gong, you know
what's happening. And what he did was he got all of the
טמאי tamei people who still had to bring their קרבנות. korbanos. Because
a lot, I know, that's what you would think. Because טמאי, tamei,
there's certain טומאות tumas which only end with the bringing of a
קרבן. korban. So what he did is he got all of them
there so they would get to jump to the front of the
line. Like, you know, like when you're getting on the plane, right?
Anybody with small children? Anybody who's טמא, you come to the front
of the line. And that's a much nicer explanation.
All right,
the שער Shaar is the one we're talking about right over here?
Yeah, yeah. But so there was no actual gate at all in
any time for the עזרת נשים, Ezras Nashim, right? Is that what...
No, there was a gate, there's a שער עזרת
נשים.
Shaar Ezras
Nashim.
Here it is, it's this is a
שער. Shaar. The כהנים Kohanim opened the gate. When?
When did they open it?
We haven't got to it yet. Okay? We're not done with it,
we're not
done with all the עבודות avodos they did before they opened. We're
seeing it in the future, that's what he's doing, getting ready to
do that.
Oh,
oh, I see, that's interesting. Yeah.
It's a good point. Maybe he had access to it, maybe שער
מזרח, Sha'ar Mizrach, that's a good point.
That's a good point. How was he in—how did he get into
the שער מזרח? Sha'ar Mizrach? How had they already opened the שער
Sha'ar for the עזרת נשים? Ezrat Nashim?
Maybe they had already opened the שער Sha'ar for the עזרת נשים
Ezrat Nashim and it didn't say. Let me look into that, get
back to that—that's a good question. But Michael is right, you can't
get to the front of the gates of the עזרה Azara unless
you went through the עזרת נשים. Ezrat Nashim. So that is a
good point. All right. So let's keep on going now. Oh my
gosh, we're falling behind here. התחילו עולים במעלות האולם. Heichilu olim b'maalot
ha'ulam.
So they started going up the steps leading to the אולם. Ulam.
If you look in your picture there are steps leading up to
the אולם. Ulam. Okay. Now the אולם Ulam does not have a
gate. It was like an open thing that went ultimately, like a
space. You know what this is also a good thing to compare
it to? What our שול shul just did. That it's got a
way, you know, it's got that what I call the butterfly zone.
You know the way the butterfly zone works is that they have
two different doors so that when you open one, the butterfly can't
get out. So we have like this little space before the main
sanctuary, right? So anyway, so that's what we have here. Right, right,
right.
That
has to be.
Oh, right, like at the אולם. Ulam. Right, right.
Anyway, so anyway, this could
also be the Israeli embassy here, you know. You can't go without
the second door.
Oh, okay.
So there you go. So they didn't have that because the outer
thing wasn't a door, it was just open. But you went through
this space and then you're, you know, and then you're in this
like little, you know, antichamber, whatever it is, before you enter into
the היכל. Heichal. So and there were steps going up to that.
התחילו עולים במעלות האולם. Heichilu olim b'maalot ha'ulam. So they went up
to the, and all of this, this entire thing is a roofed
structure, meaning the roof extends—it looks to you like it's one big
unit, the אולם Ulam with the עזרה, Azara, although you have to
go into a door before you get into the actual—not the עזרה,
Azara, in the היכל. Heichal. But it's one big sort of, you
know, roofed structure. Okay. So you went up the steps. מי שזכה
בדישון מזבח הפנימי והמנורה. Mi she'zachah b'dishun mizbe'ach hapnimi vehamenorah.
Now before you do the קטורת ketores you have to finish the
cleaning, you know, the removing the ashes from the מנורה menorah and
from the מזבח הפנימי. mizbe'ach hapnimi. This is the second half of
the previous עבודה avodah we talked about before. There actually is a
lot of debate in the ראשונים Rishonim and in the גמרא Gemara
about what the exact order was. We're just going to read it
like the פשט pshat of these משניות. mishnayot. Okay. היו מקדימים לפניהם.
Hayu makdimin lifneichem.
So those two that had to finish with the ashes, they ran—they
went ahead, they went first. מי שזכה בדישון המזבח הפנימי. Mi she'zachah
b'dishun hamizbe'ach hapnimi. The one who got the—you know, got the right
for cleaning out the inner מזבח, mizbe'ach, it sounds like it was
the same one from before. נכנס, nichnas, he went in. ונטל את
הטני, v'natal et hateni, he took the basket. Remember the basket was
filled with ashes. השתחוה, hishtachavah, he bowed down. ויצא, v'yatza, and he
left. Now why was he משתחוה? mishtachaveh? So there's a sense that
when you go into the היכל Heichal you are actually in like,
you know, the inner sanctum, you're in like the King's throne room.
So, you know, so when you enter the room before you leave,
you do a prostration, you know, to show your asking of leave
and a sign of כבוד. kavod. He didn't do it when he
entered. He didn't do it when he entered? True. I don't know
when people go into, I don't know how they did it in
ancient times, did they first השתחויה hishtachaviyah when you enter a throne
room and before you exit? Anyway, but I think that's sort of
the symbolism. And so he did the השתחויה hishtachaviyah before he left.
מי שזכה בדישון המנורה. Mi she'zachah b'dishun hamenorah. The one who merited
cleaning up the מנורה. menorah. Remember he had left two lamps burning.
נכנס ומצא שני נרות מערביים דולקים. nichnas umatza shteinei nerot maaravim dolkim.
The two western ones were burning. Question what means western, because it
might have been actually the two easternmost, but it was called western
because the second one was west relative to the first. There's a
whole debate of course what that means, but he had left two
of them burning, two of the lamps. And by the way, if
they hadn't been burning, he restarted them so that they would be
burning by this stage. Right, right. We said
that. So now he's got two left to do. מדשן את המזרחים.
Midashan et hamizrachim. Now he would not clean out both of them.
He would only clean out the easternmost one. ומניח את המערבי דולק.
u'maniach et hamaaravi dolek. And he would leave the western one—again, whatever
it means, maybe it means the one west from the east, whatever,
the second
one—burning, דולק. dolek. Why? שממנו היה מדליק את המנורה שבין הערבים. Shemimmennu
hayah madlik et hamenorah shebein ha'arbayim. Because this is the one he's
going to use—you're going to light the מנורה menorah from the נר
המערבי. ner hamaaravi. So whichever the נר המערבי ner hamaaravi was, you
would leave it now to continue to burn so you could use
it, so you did at least one more so you're still doing
the דישון, dishun, but you're going to leave this one to burn
in order that it can continue to use it at the night.
Of course, what happens if it got extinguished? Right? Well, you already
added oil, you know, earlier if you found it was extinguished. Anyway,
מצאו. matzo. Still are doing the דישון dishun but you're going to
leave this one to burn in order that it's in continue use
it at the night. Of course. What happens if it got extinguished,
right? Or while you already added oil earlier if you found that
it would extinguish. Anyway, מצאו שכבה, matzo shekava, if you see that
it extinguished, by I assume if you see it's going to run
out of oil, מדשנו ומדליקו ממזבח העולה, midashno umadliko mimizbe'ach ha'olah, then
you clean it out and you relight it from the מזבח העולה
mizbe'ach ha'olah because here's the interesting thing. You want to light the
מנורה menorah from the נר מערבי. ner maaravi. Where do you light
the נר מערבי ner maaravi from if you need to relight it?
So if you need to relight it and everything else is extinguished,
you relight it from the outer מזבח, mizbe'ach. the מזבח העולה, mizbe'ach
ha'olah, why? Because the גמרא gemara learns a פסוק pasuk because it
says by the עולה olah it says אש תמיד תוקד על המזבח,
esh tamid tukad al hamizbe'ach, and by the מנורה menorah it says
that it burns תמיד, tamid, לפני ה' תמיד, lifnei Hashem tamid, so
you light the תמיד tamid from the תמיד tamid and you light
it and you get fire from the outer מזבח. mizbe'ach Yeah, it's
a good question. Did he take a coal? Did he take a
wick? I don't know. You know, they didn't have like the paraffin
types of things.
Was it coals?
Maybe a stick. I mean the smartest thing would be to take
a match, a stick. Anyway, נטל את הכוז, natal et hakoz, anyway,
so, so, you know,
so anyway it was manipulated so that there would be two candles
left to do, and then it was manipulated again or whatever it
had to be to make sure that the western candle was could
still burn in for the evening so you could use it to
light the other ones. נטל את הכוז natal et hakoz and he
took the sort of the pitcher which had in it all the,
you know, oil and the wicks and the gook. ממעלה שנייה mima'alah
shniyah was on the second step. השתחווה ויצא hishtachava v'yatza and he
bowed down and he left. I did want to go back to
the point I forgot what David said about the throwing of this
thing בין האולם ולמזבח bein ha'ulam v'lamizbe'ach because I haven't connected it
to the מילואים miluim by אהרן aharon by the כהן גדול kohen
gadol about the, but I was thinking about the same type of
function, right? Because what does the תורה torah say about having the
bells? It says ונשמע קולו בבואו אל הקודש ולא ימות. v'nishmah kolo
b'vo'o el hakodesh v'lo yamut.
So there's some sense about the idea that, and maybe this is
also a little bit of Michael's question about bowing down before you
go in. Although it's interesting, the כהנים kohanim had already gone in
to do, start the cleaning up. But the idea to do a
real עבודה, avodah, the idea to do קטורת. ketoret. And there's some
sense like you are about to enter this space, you know, you
sort of let the fact that you're about to enter, you know,
be heard. So I think there's also some symbolic sense. They didn't
throw this thing anywhere; they threw it בין האולם ולמזבח Bein HaUlam
V'LaMizbeach. because now they're finally this is the first time you're about
to enter to do the עבודה, avodah, an עבודה avodah in the
היכל. heichal. They had entered earlier to clean the ashes, so you
know, you're entering into this space, so you're sort of let, you
know, making your presence known before you enter in. I have a
sense that that there's something sort of symbolic about that. I hadn't
connected it to the to the כהן גדול, kohen gadol, but you're
right, it's very similar. Okay, so now we continue. משנה ב'. mishna
beis. מי שזכה
במחתה, mi shezacha b'machtah, now we're doing the קטורת. ketoret. The person
that got the shovel צבר את הגחלים על גבי המזבח. tsiber et
hagechalim al gabei hamizbe'ach. He put the coals on top of the
of the gold מזבח Mizbeach? now that they finished cleaning out the
ashes and they did their bowing down. Now the קטורת ketoret כהנים
kohanim come in. So the first one put it on top of
the gold altar ורידדן בשולי המחתה. v'ridadan b'shulei hamachtah. He flattened them
with the underside of the shovel because you want them spread out.
You don't want a big heaping mound. You want to distribute the
קטורת. ketoret. You want it spread out. So he flattened them with
the underside of the shovel השתחווה ויצא. hishtachava v'yatza. He bowed down
and he left. Now מי שזכה בקטורת, mi shezacha b'ktoret, the one
who got the actual incense, היה נוטל את הבזך, haya notel et
habazach, he took the בזך bazach which was the smaller of the
pots מתוך הכף mitoch hakaf from the larger of the pots ונתנו
לאוהבו או לקרובו. v'nosno l'ohavo o l'krovo. He gave it to his
friend or to his relative. Now what did he give? It sounds
like he gave the actual קטורת, ketoret, but who would give the
קטורת ketoret away? That was the whole thing he won! So a
lot of the מפרשים meforshim say no, it means that he gave
the bigger pot to his friend. Here, you hold on to this
big pot, I got to now do the קטורת. ketoret. Okay, which
is funny, and where did that guy come in from? Like we
never it sounded like there were two people. Now we find out
there are three people. Okay.
Isn't wasn't the same guy that did the coals?
Didn't sound like it. It says somebody else, his friend, so okay.
נתפזרו ממנו לתוכה. nitpazru mimenu l'tochah. So some of the ashes might
have scattered into it from the בזך bazach into the larger one.
So then נתנו לו בחפנה. nosno lo b'chofnah. So if here I
am, you can understand it's a two-person job. Here Michael here is
holding on to the big pot, I've got the smaller one and
I'm trying to get it all into my into my you know
into my into my hands which is said to be one of
the more difficult עבודות. avodot. How do I pour into my hands
and also manipulate the pot? Okay, but anyway I'm pouring into my
hands. So if anything is spilling out, it's I'm doing it over
the larger pot. It's spilling into the larger pot. Now there's some
קטורת ketoret at the bottom of the larger pot. Now how am
I going to get it? My hands are full! So Michael, and
this is why I need a helper, is going to take the
stuff that spilled out and is now in the larger pot and
put it back into my hand.
But but what you did the first time, am I is somebody
else somebody else is holding that larger pot? Yeah.
Yeah, you're holding the larger pot, I manipulate the smaller one to
get the stuff into my hand, some is spilling out and now
you're going to help me take the overspill and put it back.
So that you can't put any of this on are you allowed
to just like put it on the floor and do it there
or are you not allowed to because it wouldn't be מכובד?
mechubad? Yeah, I mean I don't know if you're not allowed to,
but they certainly didn't, and probably exactly that. Where did that come?
Where did that קטורת Ktoret come from originally here?
In other words, how, where would they make it? Where did they
make it? Yeah, well they made it, one of these rooms here
was where they made the קטורת. Ktoret. You're right, it didn't say
that how he scooped it out and got it into the vessel
to begin with. Yeah, right. He got it from the לשכת הקטורת,
Lishkat HaKtoret, which was one of the rooms. Right, but it's interesting
that it mentioned that step of the process. Okay, now, so נתנו
לו, Natnu Lo, so Michael now, some stuff spilled into the larger
pot, Michael collects it, ונתנו לו בחפניו, V'Natnu Lo B'Chofnav, and puts
it into my hand-rests, I mean what do you call it, hand-rests,
I don't know. מלמדין אותו, Melamdin Oto,
now people who had done the job before would teach him, give
him some advice, the guy who's about to do it, and they
would say, הוי זהיר שמא תתחיל מפניך, Hevei Zahir Shema Tatchil Mifanecha,
be careful not to start doing, dropping the קטורת Ktoret near you
and moving out, because if you did that what's gonna happen? If
you start, then you're gonna burn. This is gonna start smoking, your
hand's gonna be over the smoke. So don't start close to you,
שלא תכווה, Shelo Tikaveh, you shouldn't be burned. Start from far away
and move closer towards you when you're scattering the קטורת Ktoret on
the top. התחיל מרדד ויוצא, Hitchil Meraded V'Yotzei,
he began to pour it out, מרדד Meraded again, the word from
before means like to lay it flat, so some just say it
means like he sort of held his hands like you know like
you would be sifting flour through your hands so it would come
out, you know,
not in a big lump, it would come out, you know, scattered.
What's the word here? Anyway,
so anyway, it would come out like a smooth layer and he
did that ויוצא V'Yotzei and he would leave. לא היה המקטיר מקטיר
עד שהממונה אומר לו הקטר, Lo Haya HaMaktir Maktir Ad SheHaMemuneh Omer
Lo Hakter,
the מקטיר Maktir would not do it until the person appointed said
הקטר, Hakter, you know,
do the incense. ואם היה, V'Im Haya, it's interesting, where is he
though? Is he in the מזבח? Mizbeach Is he in there? Now
we have a fourth guy in there? I mean, was he just,
he just got a, he had a say, I gave him a
few minutes, so now I'm gonna make a yell out this announcement?
I don't know. אם היה כהן גדול, הממונה אומר לו אישי
כהן גדול הקטר. Im Haya Kohen Gadol, HaMemuneh Omer Lo Ishi Kohen
Gadol Hakter. And if he was a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, he
said, he said, Mr. כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, you know, do the
הקטרה. Haktara. I was so funny, all of a sudden we're mentioning
the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, you know? Why didn't he say about
anything else? But maybe because כהן גדול Kohen Gadol would like doing
the הקטרת, Haktoret, as we're about to do in the last line,
next line, יום כפור, Yom Kippur, right? And the, which is done
by the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and going into the קודש קדשים
Kodesh Kodashim and doing, you know, and doing the קטורת Ktoret and
so on. פרשו העם, Pirshu HaAm, so then people separated, left. המקטיר,
HaMaktir, he did the קטורת, Ktoret, והשתחוה ויצא, V'Hishtachaveh V'Yatzei, he bowed
down and left. Now what does פרשו העם Pirshu HaAm mean? So
this is very much similar to what we learned from יום כפור.
Yom Kippur. I'm not sure people are aware of this, but you
know, כל אדם לא יהיה באהל מועד בבואו לכפר בקודש עד צאתו,
Kol Adam Lo Yihyeh B'Ohel Moed B'Vo'o Lechaper BaKodesh Ad Tzeito, nobody
should be in the אהל מועד, Ohel Moed, the היכל, Heichal, when
he comes in. And what we say that means is not only
on יום כפור, Yom Kippur, anytime you are doing a כפרה Kapara
inside of the היכל, Heichal, nobody else can be around. So when
you do, like when you do some of the קרבנות, Korbanot, a
few קרבנות, Korbanot, you do this זריקת הדם Zrikat HaDam inside the
היכל, Heichal, not just on יום כפור, Yom Kippur, like you know
פר העלם דבר של ציבור Par Helam Davar Shel Tzibur when the
בית דין Beit Din rules incorrectly and everybody follows them, nobody can
be around. And when you do the קטורת, Ktoret, the קטורת Ktoret
is also understood to be a type of כפרה, Kapara, right? I
mean, think about אהרן, Aharon, right? You know, when there's a מגפה,
Mageifa, he does the קטורת, Ktoret, it's מכפר Mechaper על בני ישראל.
Al Bnei Yisrael. And therefore nobody else can be around. Now where
did they have to leave? So it says from other גמרות, Gemarot,
not here, they were פורש. Poresh. Remember I told you that there's
this space בין האולם ולמזבח. Bein HaUlam V'LaMizbeach. So they didn't just
leave the היכל Heichal and the אולם, Ulam, they actually, they left
the space between the מזבח and the אולם Ulam and they got
themselves over there. So that space is very much seen as like
this, you know, the space leading up to the היכל Heichal and
somehow it's in an extended way like connected to the היכל. Heichal.
What?
You know it says באהל מועד? B'Ohel Moed? Ah, so Michael says
it says באהל מועד.
B'Ohel Moed. So what we say is yes, because there he's doing
the הקטרה Haktara in the קודש קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim. So when he's
more inner, it's enough for people to be out of the היכל.
Heichal. But when you're doing the כפרה Kapara in the היכל, Heichal,
then they have to be even more further out and they're out,
sort of like פלג המנחה Plag HaMincha on, you know, it's not
yet שבת, but it's already like they didn't say
they have to leave from the
אולם Ulam and בין האולם ולמזבח. Bein HaUlam V'LaMizbeach, Yeah, I understand.
But that's why there's this symbolic sense of the space בין האולם
ולמזבח, Bein HaUlam V'LaMizbeach. which we also saw before that when he's
about to enter, he makes the sound בין האולם ולמזבח. So even
though there were these other people, the one with the big pot,
the person saying הקטר, Hakter, maybe he was there in with him,
but right when he's about to do it, now okay fine I
got it everybody get out and everybody had to leave and then
he goes ahead and he does it. Yes.
This guy's yelling until everyone's clear? What? Maybe this guy's yelling until
everyone's clear, you can do the,
oh no, it's not like everybody, even the guy who is, oh
he first says all clear then give me a minute to get
out and then he goes out? Could be.
Okay, remember where did he throw that
noise-making, no, no, no,
just in this space, on the floor. Oh. Okay, so we will
end here. We fell back a דף, Daf, but tomorrow we will
finish. And begin תמיד. Tamid. הדרן עלך מסכת מדות. Hadran alach Masechet
Middos. הדרן עלך מסכת מדות Hadran alach Masechet Middos ודעתן עלך מסכת
מדות veda'atan alach Masechet Middos לא תתנשי מינן מסכת מדות lo sisnashi
minan Masechet Middos ולא נתנשי מינך לא בעלמא הדין ולא בעלמא דאתי.
velo nisanashi minech lo be'alma hadein velo be'alma de'asei. מסכת תמיד. Masechet
Tamid. פרק ראשון. Perek Rishon. בשלושה מקומות הכהנים שומרים בבית המקדש. Bishlosha
mekomos hakohanim shomrim beveis hamikdash. In three places the כהנים kohanim watch
in the בית המקדש: Beis Hamikdash בבית אבטינס, beveis avtinas, ובבית הניצוץ,
uveveis hanitzotz, ובבית המוקד. uveveis hamoked. והלוים בעשרים ואחד מקום. Vehalviyim be'esrim
ve'echad makom. And the לויים Leviyim in twenty-one places. חמישה על חמישה
שערי הבית. Chamisha al chamisha sha'arei habayis. Five by the five gates
of the הבית. habayis. וארבעה על ארבע פינותיו מבפנים. Ve'arba'a al arba
pinosav mibifnim. And four on the four corners on the inside. וחמישה
על חמישה שערי העזרה. Vachamisha al chamisha sha'arei ha'azarah. And five on
the five gates of the עזרה. azarah. וארבעה על ארבע פינותיה מבחוץ.
Ve'arba'a al arba pinoseha mibachutz. And four on the four corners on
the outside. ואחד בלשכת הקרבן. Ve'echad belishkas hakorban. And one in the
chamber of the sacrifice. ואחד בלשכת הפרוכת. Ve'echad belishkas haparoches. And one
in the chamber of the curtain. ואחד אחורי בית הכפורת. Ve'echad achorei
beis hakapores. And one behind the holy of holies. So what does
it mean they keep watch? What are they watching? There's no thieves
there? It says in the משנה Mishnah in the fifth פרק perek
of מדות, Middos, we have it on דף ל״ו, daf lamed vav,
it says there that the שמירה shmirah of the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash. is only לכבוד. lechavod. For the honor of the בית המקדש.
Not because we're afraid someone's going to steal something. A palace which
has no guards is not an honorable palace. So the guards were
there simply to show the greatness and the honor of the place.
Which is why the לויים Leviyim and the כהנים kohanim are there.
Why do you need both? Why not just כהנים? kohanim? Why not
just לויים? Leviyim? So the גמרא Gemara says because the more guards
there are, the more honorable it is. The גמרא Gemara says אינו
דומה פלטין שיש עליה שומרין לפלטין שאין עליה שומרין. eino domeh paltin
sheyesh aleha shomrin lepaltin she'ein aleha shomrin. A palace that has guards
is not like a palace that doesn't have guards. It shows respect.
So there were twenty-four places where they were watching. Three of them
were by כהנים kohanim and twenty-one by לויים. Leviyim.